Democracy is in trouble, no question about that,
الديمقراطية تواجه مشكلة بلا شك،
and it comes in part from a deep dilemma
وهي تشكل جزء لا يتجزأ
in which it is embedded.
من مشكلة عميقة.
It's increasingly irrelevant to the kinds of decisions
نجدها على نحو متزايد غير متعلقة بالقرارات
we face that have to do with global pandemics,
التي نواجهها، مثل الأوبئة
a cross-border problem;
وهي مشكلة عابرة للحدود
with HIV, a transnational problem;
مرض الإيدز الذي يشكل مشكلة لأكثر من دولة
with markets and immigration,
مع الأسواق والهجرة،
something that goes beyond national borders;
شيء يتعدى حدود الوطن،
with terrorism, with war,
مع الإرهاب، مع الحروب
all now cross-border problems.
أصبحت الآن جميعها مشاكل عالمية
In fact, we live in a 21st-century world
في الواقع، نحن نعيش في عالم القرن الحادي والعشرين
of interdependence,
عصر التكافل
and brutal interdependent problems,
وعصر المشاكل الوحشية المترابطة
and when we look for solutions in politics and in democracy,
وعندما نبحث عن حلول في السياسة والديمقراطية،
we are faced with political institutions
نواجه منظمات سياسية
designed 400 years ago,
تم تأسيسها قبل 400 سنة
autonomous, sovereign nation-states
مستقلة، وذات سيادة ذاتية
with jurisdictions and territories
وسلطة قضائية وذات أقاليم
separate from one another,
متفرقة عن بعضها البعض
each claiming to be able to solve the problem
وكل منها يزعم قدرته على حل هذه المشاكل
of its own people.
لشعبه
Twenty-first-century, transnational world
في القرن الحادي والعشرين، المشاكل
of problems and challenges,
والتحديات عالمية،
17th-century world of political institutions.
والمنظمات السياسية من القرن السابع عشر.
In that dilemma lies the central problem of democracy.
هذه هي المشكلة التي تواجهها الديمقراطية.
And like many others, I've been thinking about
ومثل الكثير من الأشخاص، جلست أفكر عن
what can one do about this, this asymmetry
كيفية حل هذا , هذا اللاتناسق
between 21st-century challenges
بين تحديات القرن الحادي والعشرين
and archaic and increasingly dysfunctional
والمنظمات السياسية المهجورة والمختلة
political institutions like nation-states.
مثل الدول القومية.
And my suggestion is
واقتراحي هو
that we change the subject,
أن نغير الموضوع،
that we stop talking about nations,
فلا نتحدث عن القومية،
about bordered states,
ولا نتحدث عن الدول
and we start talking about cities.
ولكن بدلًا من ذلك، نبدأ بالتحدث عن المدن.
Because I think you will find, when we talk about cities,
والسبب في نظري هو أننا عندما نتحدث عن المدن
we are talking about the political institutions
فإننا نتحدث عن منظمات سياسية
in which civilization and culture were born.
ولدت في ثقافتها وحضارتها.
We are talking about the cradle of democracy.
نحن نتحدث عن بداية الديمقراطية.
We are talking about the venues in which
نحن نتحدث عن الأماكن العامة
those public spaces where we come together
التي نجتمع فيها
to create democracy, and at the same time
لنبدأ الديمقراطية، وفي نفس الوقت
protest those who would take our freedom, take place.
نحتج ضد من يريد سلب حريتنا.
Think of some great names:
فكروا بأسماء عظيمة:
the Place de la Bastille,
بلاس دي لاباستيل
Zuccotti Park,
متنزه زوكاتي
Tahrir Square,
ميدان التحرير
Taksim Square in today's headlines in Istanbul,
ميدان تقسيم في عناوين الجرائد اليوم في إسطنبول
or, yes,
ونعم
Tiananmen Square in Beijing.
ميدان تيانمان في بكين
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Those are the public spaces
هذه هي الأماكن العامة
where we announce ourselves as citizens,
التي نعلن فيها عن أنفسنا كمواطنين،
as participants, as people with the right
وكمشاركين، وكأشخاص لهم الحق
to write our own narratives.
في كتابة قصتهم.
Cities are not only the oldest of institutions,
المدن ليست ذات مؤسسات قديمة فقط،
they're the most enduring.
ولكنها الأطول تحمُّلًا.
If you think about it,
لو فكرتم بذلك،
Constantinople, Istanbul, much older than Turkey.
القسطنطينية (إسطنبول) أقدم بكثير من تركيا.
Alexandria, much older than Egypt.
الإسكندرية، أقدم بكثير من مصر.
Rome, far older than Italy.
روما، أقدم بكثير من إيطاليا.
Cities endure the ages.
المدن تبقى عبر العصور.
They are the places where we are born,
هي الأماكن التي نولد فيها،
grow up, are educated, work, marry,
وفيها ننشأ، نتعلم، نعمل، نتزوج،
pray, play, get old, and in time, die.
نصلِّي، نلعب، نكبر، ومع الوقت نموت.
They are home.
المدن هي الوطن.
Very different than nation-states,
المدن مختلفة تمامًا عن الدول القومية،
which are abstractions.
والتي تعتبر افكار تجريدية
We pay taxes, we vote occasionally,
ندفع الضرائب، ونقوم بالتصويت بين الحين والآخر،
we watch the men and women we choose rule
ونشاهد الرجل والمرأة الذين اخترناهما ليحكموا،
rule more or less without us.
ويحكموا تقريبًا بدون تدخل منَّا.
Not so in those homes known as our towns
ليس مثل الأوطان التي نعرفها كبلداتنا
and cities where we live.
ومدننا حيث نعيش.
Moreover, today, more than half of the world's population
فوق ذلك، حاليًّا، أكثر من نصف سكان العالم
live in cities.
يعيشون في المدن.
In the developed world, it's about 78 percent.
في الدول المتقدمة، تبلغ نسبة سكان المدن 78%.
More than three out of four people
أكثر من ثلاثة لكل أربعة أشخاص
live in urban institutions, urban places,
يعيشون في مؤسسات وأماكن متحضرة
in cities today.
في المدن حاليا.
So cities are where the action is.
لذلك؛ المدن هي التي تكون فيها الحركة
Cities are us. Aristotle said in the ancient world,
المدن هي نحن. قال أرسطو في العصر القديم:
man is a political animal.
الإنسان هو حيوان سياسي.
I say we are an urban animal.
وأقول أنا: نحن حيوانات متحضرة
We are an urban species, at home in our cities.
نحن مخلوقات متحضرة، في بيوتنا ومدننا.
So to come back to the dilemma,
لذلك لنعود للمشكلة،
if the dilemma is we have old-fashioned
وهي أن لدينا دولة قومية من الطراز القديم
political nation-states unable to govern the world,
عاجزة عن حوكمة العالم،
respond to the global challenges that we face
ردا عل الصعوبات التي نواجهها
like climate change,
مثل مشكلة التغير المناخي
then maybe it's time for mayors to rule the world,
اذا فربما حان الوقت للمحافظين ان يحكموا العالم
for mayors and the citizens and the peoples they represent
للمحافظين و المواطنين و الناس الذين يمثلونهم
to engage in global governance.
لتتدخل في حكم العالم
When I say if mayors ruled the world,
عندما اقول لو ان المحافظين حكموا العالم
when I first came up with that phrase,
اول مرة اختلقت هذة الجملة
it occurred to me that actually, they already do.
يخطر علي بالي انهم بالفعل يحكمون العالم
There are scores of international, inter-city,
هناك العشرات من المؤسسات الدولية و بين المدن
cross-border institutions, networks of cities
و مؤسسات تتعدي الحدود , شباكات من المدن
in which cities are already, quite quietly,
و التي فيها المدن في هدوء
below the horizon, working together
تعمل معاً ,تحت الافق
to deal with climate change, to deal with security,
لتتعامل مع تغير الطقس, لتتعامل مع الامن
to deal with immigration,
لتتعامل مع الهجرة
to deal with all of those tough,
لتتعامل مع كل هذة
interdependent problems that we face.
المشاكل المترابطة الصعبة التي نواجهها
They have strange names:
لها اسماء غريبة
UCLG,
UCLG
United Cities and Local Governments;
المدن المتحدة و الحكومات المحلية
ICLEI,
ICLEI
the International Council for Local Environmental Issues.
المجلس الدولي للقضايا البيئية المحلية
And the list goes on:
و القائمة تطول
Citynet in Asia; City Protocol, a new organization
Citynet في اسيا ; City Protocol منظمة جديدة
out of Barcelona that is using the web
خرجت من بارشيلونا و التي تستخدم الشبكة
to share best practices among countries.
لمشاركة افضل الممارسات بين المدن
And then all the things we know a little better,
و ايضا كل الاشياء التي نعرفها افضل اكثر
the U.S. Conference of Mayors,
مؤتمر الولايات المتحدة للمحافظين
the Mexican Conference of Mayors,
المؤتمر المكسيكي للمحافظين
the European Conference of Mayors.
المؤتمر الاوروبي للمحافظين
Mayors are where this is happening.
المحافظين موجودين حيث كل هذا يحدث
And so the question is,
و هنا السؤال هو
how can we create a world
كيف نخلق عالم
in which mayors and the citizens they represent
التي فيها المحافظين و المواطنين الذين يمثلونهم
play a more prominent role?
يلعبون دور اكثر بروزا
Well, to understand that,
حسنا لنفهم هذا
we need to understand why cities are special,
نحتاج لفهم لماذا المدن بهذة الاستثنائية
why mayors are so different
لماذا العمداء مختلفون
than prime ministers and presidents,
عن رؤساء الوزراء و الرؤساء
because my premise is that a mayor and a prime minister
لان في افتراضي ان العمدة و رئيس الوزراء
are at the opposite ends of a political spectrum.
هم علي الطرفين من الطيف السياسي
To be a prime minister or a president,
ان تكون رئيس وزراء او رئيس
you have to have an ideology,
يجب ان يكون لك ايدولوجية
you have to have a meta-narrative,
يجب ان يكون متحدث لبق
you have to have a theory of how things work,
يجب ان يكون لديك نظرية عن كيفية عمل الاشياء
you have to belong to a party.
يجب ان تنتمي لحزب
Independents, on the whole,
متسقلين, عامة
don't get elected to office.
لا يتم انتخابة لمصبه
But mayors are just the opposite.
لكن المحافظين عن العكس تمام
Mayors are pragmatists, they're problem-solvers.
العمداء هم برجماتيين , هم محلين مشاكل
Their job is to get things done, and if they don't,
وظيفتهم هي تسيير الامور, و اذا لم يسييروها
they're out of a job.
يخرجون من الوظيفة
Mayor Nutter of Philadelphia said,
المحافظ ناتر من فيلاديلفيا قال
we could never get away here in Philadelphia
لا يمكننا العمل هنا في فيلاديلفيا
with the stuff that goes on in Washington,
بنفس الاشياء التي تعمل في واشنطن
the paralysis, the non-action, the inaction.
الشلل, اللاعمل, التراخي
Why? Because potholes have to get filled,
لماذا؟,لان الحفر يجب ان تُملاء
because the trains have to run,
لان القطارات يجب ان تعمل
because kids have to be able to get to school.
لان الاطفال يجب ان يتمكنوا من الذهاب للمدارس
And that's what we have to do,
و هذا ما يجب ان نفعله
and to do that is about pragmatism
و لكي تفعل هذا يجب ان تكون براجماتي
in that deep, American sense,
في هذا العمق, الحس الامريكي
reaching outcomes.
الوصول للنتائج
Washington, Beijing, Paris, as world capitals,
واشنطن بيكين باريس كعواصم العالم
are anything but pragmatic,
هي اي شئ الا براجماتية
but real city mayors have to be pragmatists.
لكن عمداء المدن الحقيقية يجب ان يكونوا براجماتيين
They have to get things done,
يجب ان يسيروا الامور
they have to put ideology and religion and ethnicity aside
يجب ان يضعوا الايدولوجية و الدين و الانتماء العرقي جانبا
and draw their cities together.
و يبنوا مدنهم معا
We saw this a couple of decades ago
رأينا هذا منذ عقدين
when Teddy Kollek, the great mayor of Jerusalem
عندما تيدي كوليك, عمدة مدينة القدس العظيم
in the '80s and the '90s,
في الثمانينات و التسعينات
was besieged one day in his office
حوصر يوما في مكتبه
by religious leaders from all of the backgrounds,
بواسطة قادة دينين من كل الطوائف
Christian prelates, rabbis, imams.
الأساقفة المسيحيين والحاخامات و الائمة
They were arguing with one another
كانوا يتجادلون حول شئ واحد
about access to the holy sites.
حول دخول الاماكن المقدسة
And the squabble went on and on,
و الشجار استمر و استمر
and Kollek listened and listened,
و كوليك استمع و استمع
and he finally said, "Gentlemen,
و في النهاية قال "ايها السادة.
spare me your sermons,
اعيروني خطبكم
and I will fix your sewers."
و سوف اصلح مجاريكم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's what mayors do.
هذا ما يفعله المحافظين
They fix sewers, they get the trains running.
انهم يصلحون المجاري , انهم يسيرون القطارات
There isn't a left or a right way of doing.
لا يوجد طريق يمين او يسار لفعل هذا
Boris Johnson in London calls himself an anarcho-Tory.
بوريس جونسون في لندن يطلق علي نفسه المحافظ الاناركي
Strange term, but in some ways, he is.
مصطلح غريب, لكن بشكل ما, هو كذلك
He's a libertarian. He's an anarchist.
هو ليبرالي و هو اناركي
He rides to work on a bike,
يركب دراجته للعمل
but at the same time, he's in some ways a conservative.
لكن في نفس الوقت, هو بشكل ما محافظ
Bloomberg in New York was a Democrat,
بلومبرج في نيويورك كان ديموقراطي
then he was a Republican,
ثم اصبح جمهوري
and finally he was an Independent, and said
ثم اصبح مستقل و قال
the party label just gets in the way.
ان التصنيف الحزبي كان يعيقه
Luzhkov, 20 years mayor in Moscow,
لوشكوف عمدة موسكو لمدة 20 عاما
though he helped found a party, United Party with Putin,
رغم انه ساعد في انشاء حزب ,حزب روسيا المتحدة مع بوتين
in fact refused to be defined by the party
في الواقع رفض تصنيفه ضمن الحزب
and finally, in fact, lost his job not under Brezhnev,
و في النهاية في الواقع خسر وظيفته ليس في وقت حكم بريجنيف
not under Gorbachev, but under Putin,
ليس في وقت حكم جورباتشوف و لكن وقت حكم بوتن
who wanted a more faithful party follower.
الذي اراد تابعين اكثر اخلاصا للحزب
So mayors are pragmatists and problem-solvers.
اذا العمداء برجماتيين و محلين مشاكل
They get things done.
انهم يسيرون الامور
But the second thing about mayors
لكن الشئ الثاني عن المحافظين
is they are also what I like to call homeboys,
هو ما احب ان اسميه اولاد المنطقة
or to include the women mayors, homies.
او حتي نضم العمداء النساء, ابناء المنطقة
They're from the neighborhood.
هم من الحي
They're part of the neighborhood. They're known.
هم جزء من الحي, معروفين
Ed Koch used to wander around New York City
ايد كوتش اعتاد ان يتجول في نيويورك
saying, "How am I doing?"
قائلا "كيف ابليت ؟ "
wandering around the United Kingdom
يتجول في المملكة المتحدة
asking, "How am I doing?" He wouldn't like the answer.
يسأل "كيف ابليت؟" ما كان ليعجبه الاجابة
Or Putin. Or any national leader.
او بوتين او اي قائد دولي
He could ask that because he knew New Yorkers
استطاع ان يسأل هذا السؤال لانه يعرف النيويوركيين
and they knew him.
و هم يعرفونه
Mayors are usually from the places they govern.
العمداء عادة يكونوا من المكان الذي يحكمونه
It's pretty hard to be a carpetbagger and be a mayor.
من الصعب جدا ان تكون مستفيد و عمدة في نفس الوقت
You can run for the Senate out of a different state,
يمكن الترشح لمجلس الشيوخ من ولاية اخري
but it's hard to do that as a mayor.
لكن يصعب ان تفعل هذا كعمدة
And as a result, mayors and city councillors
و كنتيجة العمداء و مجالس المدن
and local authorities
و السلطة المحلية
have a much higher trust level,
لديها مستوي ثقة اعلي
and this is the third feature about mayors,
و هذة هي الصفة الثالثة المحافظين
than national governing officials.
عن مسؤولين السلطة القومية
In the United States, we know the pathetic figures:
في الولايات المتحدة نعرف الارقام المثيرة للشفقة
18 percent of Americans approve of Congress
18 في المائة من الامريكيين يوافقون علي الكونجرس
and what they do.
و ما يفعله
And even with a relatively popular president like Obama,
و حتي مع الرئيس المحبوب الي حد ما مثل اوباما
the figures for the Presidency run about 40, 45,
الرقم للرئاسة يصل ل 40 45
sometimes 50 percent at best.
احيانا 50 بالمائة في اقصي حد
The Supreme Court has fallen way down from what it used to be.
المحكمة العليا سقطت عما كانت عليه قديما
But when you ask, "Do you trust your city councillor,
لكن عندما تسأل "هل تثق في مجلس مدينتك ,
do you trust your mayor?"
هل تثق في عمدتك؟"
the rates shoot up to 70, 75, even 80 percent,
المعدل يرتفع ل 70,75 و حتي 80 في المائة
because they're from the neighborhood,
لأنهم من الحي
because the people they work with are their neighbors,
لان الناس الذين يعملون معهم من الجوار
because, like Mayor Booker in Newark,
لان مثل العمدة بووكر في نيوارك
a mayor is likely to get out of his car on the way to work
العمدة من المعتاد ان يخرج من سيارته في طريقه للعمل
and go in and pull people out of a burning building --
و يتدخل لينقذ اشخاص من مبني محترق
that happened to Mayor Booker --
هذا حدث للمحافظ بووكر
or intervene in a mugging in the street as he goes to work
او يتدخل ليمنع عملية سطو في طريقه للعمل
because he sees it.
لانه يراها
No head of state would be permitted
لا يمكن لرئيس دولة ان يسمح له
by their security details to do it,
بواسطة فريق الامن
nor be in a position to do it.
و لا ان يكون في الموقع ليفعل هذا
That's the difference, and the difference
هذا هو الاختلاف و الاختلاف
has to do with the character of cities themselves,
يجب ان يتعلق بصفات المدن نفسها
because cities are profoundly multicultural,
لان المدن متعددة الثقافات بعمق
open, participatory, democratic,
منفتحة, مشاركة, ديموقراطية
able to work with one another.
تستطيع ان تعمل معاً
When states face each other,
عدنما تتواجة الدول
China and the U.S., they face each other like this.
الصين و الولايات المتحدة يتواجهان هكذا
When cities interact, they interact like this.
عندما تتفاعل المدن تتفاعل هكذا
China and the U.S., despite the recent
الصين و الولايات المتحدة رغم
meta-meeting in California,
المقابلات العليا في كاليفورنيا
are locked in all kinds of anger, resentment, and rivalry
مصرة علي كل انواع الغضب ,الاستياء, و المنافسة
for number one.
للمركز الاول
We heard more about who will be number one.
سمعنا اكثر عن من سيكون في المركز الاول
Cities don't worry about number one.
المدن لا تقلق علي المركز الاول
They have to work together, and they do work together.
يجب ان تعمل معاً و هي تعمل معاَ
They work together in climate change, for example.
انها تعمل معاً في تغير الطقس كمثال
Organizations like the C40, like ICLEI, which I mentioned,
منظمات مثل C40 و مثل ICLEI التي ذكرتها
have been working together
كانت تعمل معاً
many, many years before Copenhagen.
لأعوام كثيرة قبل كوبنهاجن
In Copenhagen, four or five years ago,
في كوبنهاجن اربع او خمس سنوات سابقة
184 nations came together to explain to one another
184 دولة اجتمعوا لتوضح لبعضها
why their sovereignty didn't permit them
لماذا سيادتها منعتها
to deal with the grave, grave crisis of climate change,
من التعامل مع الازمة الخطيرة ازمة تغير المناخ
but the mayor of Copenhagen had invited
لكن محافظ كوبنهاجن دعا
200 mayors to attend.
200 محافظ للحضور
They came, they stayed, and they found ways
جائوا و بقوا و وجدوا طرق
and are still finding ways to work together,
و لازالوا يجدون طرق للعمل معاً
city-to-city, and through inter-city organizations.
مدينة لمدينة و خلال منظمات بين المدن
Eighty percent of carbon emissions come from cities,
ثمانين بالمائة من انبعاث الكربون يأتي من المدن
which means cities are in a position
و الذي يعني المدن مطلوبة منها
to solve the carbon problem, or most of it,
حل مشكلة الكربون او حتي معظمها
whether or not the states of which they are a part
سواء كانت او لم تكن الدول التي هي جزء منها
make agreements with one another.
تتفق مع بعضها
And they are doing it.
و هم يفعلونها
Los Angeles cleaned up its port,
لوس انجلوس نظفت مينائها
which was 40 percent of carbon emissions,
الذي كان 40 في المائة انبعاثات كربون
and as a result got rid of about 20 percent of carbon.
و كنتيجة تخلصت من 20 بالمائة من الكربون
New York has a program to upgrade its old buildings,
نيويورك لديها برنامج تحديث لمبانيها القديمة
make them better insulated in the winter,
جعلها معزولة بشكل افضل في الشتاء
to not leak energy in the summer,
و تمنع تسرب الطاقة في الصيف
not leak air conditioning. That's having an impact.
لا تمنع تسرب الهواء المكيف هذا له تأثير
Bogota, where Mayor Mockus,
بوجوتا كان محافظ موكوس
when he was mayor, he introduced a transportation system
عندما كان محافظ,قدم نظام نقل
that saved energy, that allowed surface buses
يوفر طاقة, يسمح بالحافلات
to run in effect like subways,
لتعمل في الواقع مثل قطارات الانفاق
express buses with corridors.
حافلات اكبريس ذات الابواب
It helped unemployment, because people could get across town,
تساعد في مسألة البطالة, لان الناس ستستطيع التنقل في المدينة
and it had a profound impact on climate as well as
و قد كان له تأثير جذري علي المناخ ايضا
many other things there.
اشياء اخري هناك
Singapore, as it developed its high-rises
سنغافورا عندما كانت تنمو نموها الكبير
and its remarkable public housing,
و نظام الاسكان الشعبي المعروف
also developed an island of parks,
ايضا طور جزيرة من المواقف
and if you go there, you'll see how much of it
و اذا ذهبت هناك ستري كم اصبحت
is green land and park land.
اراضي خضراء و اراضي مواقف
Cities are doing this, but not just one by one.
المدن تفعل هذا, و ليس كل علي حدا
They are doing it together.
انهم يفعلونها معاً
They are sharing what they do,
انهم يتشاركون ما يفعلون
and they are making a difference by shared best practices.
و يقومون بإحداث فرق عن طريق مشاركة افضل الممارسات
Bike shares, many of you have heard of it,
مشاركة الدراجات الكثير منكم سمع عنها
started 20 or 30 years ago in Latin America.
بدأت من 20 او 30 سنة في امريكا اللاتينية
Now it's in hundreds of cities around the world.
الان مئات المدن حول العالم
Pedestrian zones, congestion fees,
مناطق مشاة و رسوم ازدحام
emission limits in cities like California cities have,
حدود الانبعاث في المدن مثل التي في مدن كاليفورنيا
there's lots and lots that cities can do
هناك العديد و العديد من المدن
even when opaque, stubborn nations refuse to act.
حتي عندما ترفض دول منظمة اوبك العندية ان تتحرك
So what's the bottom line here?
اذا ما هو بيت القصيد هنا ؟
The bottom line is, we still live politically
بيت القصيد هنا لا نزال نعيش سياسياً
in a world of borders, a world of boundaries,
في عالم من الحدود
a world of walls,
عالم من الحوائط
a world where states refuse to act together.
عالم حيث ترفض الدول ان تعمل معاً
Yet we know that the reality we experience
مع ذلك ان الواقع الذي نعيشه
day to day is a world without borders,
يوماً بيوم هو عالم بلا حدود
a world of diseases without borders
عالم بأمراض بلاحدود
and doctors without borders,
و اطباء بلا حدود
maladies sans frontières, Médecins Sans Frontières,
امراض بلا حدود و اطباء بلا حدود
of economics and technology without borders,
اقتصاديات بلا حدود و تقنيات بلا حدود
of education without borders,
تعليم بلا حدود
of terrorism and war without borders.
ارهاب و حرب بلا حدود
That is the real world, and unless we find a way
هذا هو العالم الحقيقي و مالم نجد طريقه
to globalize democracy or democratize globalization,
لعولمة الديموقراطية او دمقرطة العولمة
we will increasingly not only risk
سوف نخاطر بشكل متزايد
the failure to address all of these transnational problems,
ليس فقط ان نفشل ان نعالج المشاكل الدولية
but we will risk losing democracy itself,
بل ايضا سنخاطر بخسارة الديموقراطية
locked up in the old nation-state box,
محبوسين في صندوق الدولة القديمة
unable to address global problems democratically.
غير قادرين علي معالجة المشاكل العالمية بشكل ديموقراطي
So where does that leave us?
لذا اين يتركنا هذا
I'll tell you. The road to global democracy
سأخبركم ,الطريق للديموقراطية العالمية
doesn't run through states.
لا تحدث عن طريق الدول
It runs through cities.
انها تحدث عن طريق المدن
Democracy was born in the ancient polis.
الديموقراطية ولدت في المدن الرومانية القديمة
I believe it can be reborn in the global cosmopolis.
انا اؤمن انها يمكن ان يعاد ولادتها في المدن العالمية
In that journey from polis to cosmopolis,
في هذة الرحلة من المدن الرومانية للمدن العالمية
we can rediscover the power
يمكننا ان نعيد اكتشاف قوة
of democracy on a global level.
الديموقراطية علي مستوي عالمي
We can create not a League of Nations, which failed,
يمكننا ان نخلق ليس عصبة الامم و التي فشلت
but a League of Cities,
بل عصبة المدن
not a United or a dis-United Nations,
ليس الامم المتحدة او الغير متحدة
but United Cities of the World.
لكن اتحاد مدن العالم
We can create a global parliament of mayors.
يمكننا ان ننشئ برلمان عالمي للمحافظين
That's an idea. It's in my conception of the coming world,
هذة فكرة , انها في تصميمي للعالم القادم
but it's also on the table in City Halls
و لكن ايضا علي طاولات مباني البلدية
in Seoul, Korea, in Amsterdam,
في سيول كوريا في امستردام,
in Hamburg, and in New York.
في هامبرج في نيويورك
Mayors are considering that idea of how you can actually
المحافظين ينظرون لفكرة كيف يمكننا
and I love that idea, because a parliament of mayors
و انا احب هذة الفكرة لان برلمان المحافظين
is a parliament of citizens
هو برلمان المواطنين
and a parliament of citizens is a parliament of us,
و برلمان المواطنين هو برلمان مننا
of you and of me.
منك و مني
If ever there were citizens without borders,
لو انه كان هناك مواطنين بلا حدود
I think it's the citizens of TED
اعتقد انهم سيكونوا مواطنين TED
who show the promise to be those citizens without borders.
الذين يبشرون بان يكونوا المواطنين بلا حدود
I am ready to reach out and embrace
انا مستعد لان نصل و نحتضن
a new global democracy,
ديموقراطية عالمية جديدة
to take back our democracy.
لاستعادة ديموقراطيتنا
And the only question is,
و السؤال الوحيد هو
are you?
هل انتم كذلك ؟
Thank you so much, my fellow citizens.
شكرا جزيلا اصحابي المواطنين
(Applause)
(تصفيق)